And now it's time to talk about
everybody's favorite transatlantic
transfer, the Columbian Exchange. Yes.
Oh, I know. I know. It's it's the best.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Okay. So,
if you watch the previous two videos,
then you'll remember that Europeans were
going crazy in the 16th century to
establish colonial empires in the
Americas, as well as doing their best to
dominate trade in the Indian Ocean. And
chief among their motivations for doing
so is to get enough wealth to make Mansa
poop his pants. And we'll talk a lot
about that in the next video. But here
you just need to know that Europeans
extracted stupid amounts of wealth from
the new world and the Indian Ocean
through trade. And there were two
specific developments that made such
trade more organized and efficient.
First, there were improvements in
maritime technology. Oh, and here's
where I remind you or you know tell you
for the first time that maritime means
sea based or you know of the sea. So
here I'm talking about technology that
made shipping over the water easier. And
let's consider a couple of examples both
of which Europeans borrowed from Muslim
and Chinese navigators. First, you had
new kinds of ships that were built for
trade, like the Portuguese Caravl, which
was very fast and highly navigable. And
one of the reasons it was fast was
because it made use of everybody's
favorite triangular wind catcher, the
Latin sail, which could take wind from
both sides and not just from behind like
square sails.
>> I know. I know. Also, Europeans adopted
the magnetic compass, which helped them
reckon direction as well as the
astrolay, which gave them accurate
reckoning of lines of latitude. Or to
say all of that real simple like they
built good boat and sailed real good.
Oh, and by the way, if you want note
guys to follow along with this video and
all my videos and have some like quizzes
to help you learn all this stuff, then
that link is in the description. Now,
the second development that facilitated
the growth of trade was the rise of the
joint stock company, which refers to a
limited liability business, often
chartered by the state and funded by a
group of investors. And all that is a
very complicated way of saying that
joint stock companies made it so that
anyone with some money could invest in
exploration with the hopes of getting a
good return. You see, funding an
exploration outfit was a real expense
and that led to two related problems.
States only had so much money that they
could invest in these ventures and it
was a pretty common occurrence that they
failed. So joint stock companies solved
both of those problems. The money came
from a pool of investors, not just a
single source like a government who
often had other demands on their
finances like you know fighting wars on
account of religion. But to be clear,
even if they were privately funded,
joint stock companies still relied on
the state to keep their interest and
activities safe while also granting them
monopolies on various regions of trade.
Anyway, the point is because this new
way of financing exploration opened
investment to a whole lot more people
who could potentially strike it rich
that had the effect of multiplying
expeditions and creating more trade
routes around the world. Okay, so those
are two of the causes of increased
maritime trade during this period. But
now let's get to the juicy stuff and
talk about the effects. And there is one
massive honking effect that's going to
consume our entire horizon in this
video, namely the Colombian exchange,
which occurred as a result of all this
exploration and contact across the
Atlantic Ocean that we've been talking
about. And as is proper, I reckon we
ought to start with a definition. So the
Columbian exchange refers to the
transfer of diseases, plants, animals,
minerals, and people between the old and
new world. And by the way, when I say
old world, I mean this part of the
world. And then new world refers to this
part of the world. Okay. Now, I don't
think it's too much to say that the
Columbian exchange was one of the most
significant developments in the history
of the world because it led to
fundamental changes on both sides of the
Atlantic. So let's talk about that. So
first, diseases were exchanged. Now,
because folks throughout Afroureasia had
been in contact for millennia, they
developed immunities to each other's
nasty germs. However, because of the
isolation of the indigenous peoples of
the Americas, the diseases Europeans
introduced were devastating. Now, to be
fair, there is evidence that those
diseases had been present in the
Americas prior to European contact, but
if so, it had been a long time, and so
apparently their bodies had forgotten
how to fight those particular brands of
cooties. So, for example, the Spanish
introduced smallox to the Caribbean in
1518, and it proved to be one of the
most devastating diseases set loose
among the indigenous peoples of the
Americas. On Hispanola, where Columbus
first landed, smallox was responsible
for the death of something like 90% of
the indigenous China. And from there,
the disease just followed along with
Spanish conquest through Mexico and
Central America, killing something like
half the population there. And then as
it spread through South America, it
caused a similar demographic disaster.
Additionally, the Spanish introduced
measles to the Americas, which in some
cases prove just as deadly as smallox.
So, it is for good reason that
indigenous Americans refer to this
introduction of European diseases as the
great dying. Okay. Now the second major
transfer in the Columbian exchange was
food and plants and this had major
effects on both European and indigenous
populations. European settlers
introduced wheat and olives and grapes
among many others which were staples of
European diets. And eventually they also
introduced African and Asian foods like
rice and bananas and sugar to the
Americas. And then new world crops like
maize and potatoes and manio were also
transferred to Europe. And then later
when enslaved Africans were being sent
to the Americas, they would also bring
new foods with them like okra for
example. Anyway, I'm not just naming
food items for funsies. This transfer of
foods had major impacts in both the old
and new worlds. In general, the
introduction of new foods created the
occasion for a more varied diet, which
meant healthier populations in Europe.
That led to a population explosion after
about 1700. And that's going to be a big
deal in the next period when a lot of
those people are going to immigrate to
their country's colonial holdings. And
then third, animals were a big part of
the Columbian exchange. And again,
animals went both ways, but arguably it
was the horse introduced to the Americas
by Europeans that had the most
significant impact. Using the horse
provided indigenous groups in the great
plains like the Apaches and the
Comanches and the Kyas even more
effective means to hunt large herds of
buffalo which was a staple food item for
them and it definitely gave them an
advantage in their conflicts with other
indigenous groups which shifted the
balance of power in favor of those
groups that had adopted the horse. It
was a change that fundamentally altered
their way of life. But there were other
animals introduced to the Americas as
well like pigs and sheep and cattle.
Because they had no natural predators,
they went positively hog wild and
multiply. And that definitely caused
some problems since sheep ate metric
buttloads of grass causing erosion that
affected indigenous farmers and pigs and
cattle had a habit of trampling and
eating indigenous crops. And finally,
the fourth major category of transfer in
the Columbian exchange was minerals, the
chief of which was silver and gold. And
so, for example, as Spanish concistadors
conquered major powers like the Aztec
and the Inca empires, they plundered
them for their massive quantities of
gold and silver and that made Spain uh
real rich. Now later on the Spanish
would discover that the export of cash
crops from the new world was also highly
profitable. But at least in the
beginning their entire focus was on
getting that gold and silver. For
example, this mountain right here is
called Possi which today is located in
southern Bolivia. And the Spanish loved
this mountain because it was packed with
metric buttloads of silver that was
extracted by the hands of enslaved
indigenous people. But the Spanish
weren't all that worried about them
because so much silver was being pumped
into the European economy via Spain that
two massive effects occurred. First, the
price revolution occurred in which
prices for European goods rose pretty
steadily for about a century and a half.
And then second, and intimately related,
this economic change hastened the shift
from feudalism to capitalism in some
places in Europe. And without getting
too far into the weeds, here's what that
means. So feudalism was a social and
economic arrangement that created a kind
of closed system that focused on land
ownership. But then capitalism was a
more open system that focused on
manufacturing and trade. Anyway, this
shift was a massive change and the
Colombian exchange was right there in
the middle making it all happen. All
these economic changes combined with the
growing demand for more crops and
mineral wealth in Europe is going to
have major consequences later in this
unit, specifically in terms of labor
systems and demographic changes. But far
be it for me to spoil all those
developments here. Guess we'll just have
to wait for the next video. Okay, click
here to watch my other unit one videos
and click here to grab my video note
guides which is going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain folds. And hey,
I'll catch you on the flipflop. I'm
Lorett.